Finding Aid for Ralph L. Belknap papers, ca. 1926-1933 and 1957-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ralph L. Belknap papers ca. 1926-1933, 1957-1973
Belknap, Ralph Leroy, 1899-
0.4 linear ft. and 1 reel of microfilm; 1 16mm film and DVD use copy
8581 Aa 2 Aa microcopy
Professor of geology at the University of Michigan; Correspondence, journal, photographs, film and other materials relating to the University's 1926-1933 scientific expeditions to Greenland.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Belknap in 1992, (Donor: 5654 ).
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The 16mm film in the collection was digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes for all titles and high resolution digital files of some titles were created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A streaming version of the film is linked below.
Ralph LeRoy Belknap was born in St. Clair, Michigan. He enrolled in the University of Michigan in 1918, earning a bachelors' degree in civil engineering and masters and doctoral degree while serving as an instructor in the Department of Geology. He was appointed assistant professor in 1930 and associate professor in 1939.
Belknap was chief surveyor on the university's first expedition to Green land led by professor William. Hobbs and was assistant director of the second and third expeditions. In 1932 he led a final Greenland expedition, jointly sponsored by the University of Michigan and pan American Airways to record geological and meteorological conditions in previously uncharted wastes.
He later served as director of the Meteorological Station in Ann Arbor and of the geologic study at Camp Davis in Wyoming. Belknap suffered a career ending injury from a fall at Cam p Davis in 1946. He died December 17, 1960 in Ann Arbor.
The Belknap collection consists primarily of material documenting the 1932 expedition to Greenland and the efforts to establish a memorial to Arctic explorer Admiral Richard E. Peary at Cape York, Greenland. The papers include correspondence, journal, photographs, other materials. Also included is a film of the 1926 voyage to Greenland. activities of the first expedition in Greenland.
Subjects:
Arctic regions.; Belknap, Ralph Leroy, 1899-; Greenland.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Belknap, Ralph Leroy, 1899-; Eskimos.; Expeditions and surveys.; Greenland.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Monuments and memorials.; Peary, Robert E. (Robert Edwin), 1856-1920.; Schmeling, Evans S.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Videotapes.
Genre Terms:
Dvds.; Photographs.; Diaries.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Papers
  - 1932 Expedition
    - Expedition correspondence, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
    - Expedition communiqués, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
    - Expedition miscellanea
  - Correspondence of Mrs. Belknap largely concerning Peary Monument at Cape York, undated and ca. 1955-1973 (Box 1)
  - Printed material (Box 1)
    (articles, clippings, reprints about the expeditions and a sketch of Belknap by Dan Laursen)
  - Photographs
    - Print of Evans Schmeling (Box 1)
      (he rescued Belknap during construction of Peary monument)
    - Negatives of Peary Monument at Cape York, Greenland, 10 negatives, na3103-na3112
      (stored with copy negatives )
  - Scientific Diary, ca 1926?-1933?, microfilm (Box 1)
- Motion Pictures
  - 1926 Expedition to Greenland, 1926 [8581-1]
    The1926 Expedition film includes footage of preparation of the vessel in harbor, the departure and voyage to Greenland, arrival and setting up of camp, a variety of camp and scientific activities and interaction with natives who assisted the expedition. Four original films have been combined in a single reel.
    - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:39:37
      [Restricted]
    - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
    - Streaming File: 8581-1, flv
Related Material
The William H. Hobbs papers at the Bentley Library include material on the 1926 expedition to Greenland. Hobbs' published account of the expedition "The First Greenland Expedition of the University of Michigan" (Geographical Review, Vol. 17, No. 1 (Jan., 1927), pp. 1-35, is available online trough JSTOR at http://www.jstor.org/stable/208131?seq=4
The Reports of the Greenland expeditions of the University of Michigan published by the University of Michigan press are also available at the Bentley Library.